<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Helpful resources | Data Analytics</title>
    <link>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Helpful resources</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <image>
      <url>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/img/social-image.png</url>
      <title>Helpful resources</title>
      <link>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Installing R, RStudio (Posit), tidyverse, and tinytex</title>
      <link>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/install/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/install/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#install-r&#34; id=&#34;toc-install-r&#34;&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#install-rstudioposit&#34; id=&#34;toc-install-rstudioposit&#34;&gt;Install RStudio/Posit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#install-tidyverse&#34; id=&#34;toc-install-tidyverse&#34;&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#install-tinytex&#34; id=&#34;toc-install-tinytex&#34;&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;tinytex&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the syllabus, you will do all of your work in this class with the open source programming language &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You will use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;RStudio/Posit&lt;/a&gt; as the main program to access &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;. Think of &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; as an engine and RStudio/Posit as a car dashboard—–&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; handles all the calculations and the actual statistics, while RStudio provides a nice interface for running &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RStudio is in the process of rebranding as Posit. You’ll see both along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully you’re well-versed in dealing with these things, but if you’re lost, here’s how you install the required software for the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;install-r&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have created a video walkthrough for installing R for another course, but it is useful here. You can &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.msu.edu/media/R+Part+1/1_b8nafkzx&#34;&gt;see it here &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-film&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First you need to install &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; itself (the engine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Go to the CRAN (Collective &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; Archive Network)&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; website: &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click on “Download &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;XXX&lt;/code&gt;”, where &lt;code&gt;XXX&lt;/code&gt; is either Mac or Windows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/install/install-r-links.png&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you use macOS, scroll down to the first &lt;code&gt;.pkg&lt;/code&gt; file in the list of files (in this picture, it’s &lt;code&gt;R-4.0.0.pkg&lt;/code&gt;; as of Summer 2022 now, the current version is also 4.2.1 so use the most recent one) and download it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/install/install-r-mac.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you use Windows, click “base” (or click on the bolded “install R for the first time” link) and download it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/install/install-r-windows.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Double click on the downloaded file (check your &lt;code&gt;Downloads&lt;/code&gt; folder). Click yes through all the prompts to install like any other program.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you use macOS, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.xquartz.org/&#34;&gt;download and install XQuartz&lt;/a&gt;. You do not need to do this on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;install-rstudioposit&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Install RStudio/Posit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you need to install the most recent version of RStudio, the nicer graphical user interface (GUI) for &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; (the dashboard). Once &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; and RStudio/Posit are both installed, you can ignore &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; and only use RStudio. RStudio will use &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; automatically and you won’t ever have to interact with it directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the free download location on RStudio’s website: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/#download&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.rstudio.com/products/rstudio/download/#download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The website should automatically detect your operating system (macOS or Windows) and show a big download button for it:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/install/install-r-rstudio1.png&#34; width=&#34;50%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If not, scroll down a little to the large table and choose the version of RStudio that matches your operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/install/install-r-rstudio2.png&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double click on the downloaded file (again, check your &lt;code&gt;Downloads&lt;/code&gt; folder). Click yes through all the prompts to install like any other program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Double click on RStudio to run it (check your applications folder or start menu).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;install-tidyverse&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; packages are easy to install with RStudio. Select the packages panel, click on “Install,” type the name of the package you want to install, and press enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/install/install-r-package-panel.png&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can sometimes be tedious when you’re installing lots of packages, though. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidyverse.org/&#34;&gt;The tidyverse&lt;/a&gt;, for instance, consists of dozens of packages (including the ever-present &lt;strong&gt;ggplot2&lt;/strong&gt;) that all work together. Rather than install each individually, you can install a single magical package and get them all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to the packages panel in RStudio, click on “Install,” type “tidyverse”, and press enter. You’ll see a bunch of output in the RStudio console as all the tidyverse packages are installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/install/install-r-tidyverse.png&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice also that RStudio will generate a line of code for you and run it: &lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#34;tidyverse&#34;)&lt;/code&gt;. You can also just paste and run this instead of using the packages panel. Hopefully you’ve experienced installing packages before now; if not, consider this a crash course!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;install-tinytex&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Install &lt;code&gt;tinytex&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you knit to PDF, &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; uses a special scientific typesetting program named LaTeX.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LaTeX is neat and makes pretty documents, but it’s a huge program—&lt;a href=&#34;https://tug.org/mactex/mactex-download.html&#34;&gt;the macOS version, for instance, is nearly 4 GB&lt;/a&gt;. To make life easier, there’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.org/tinytex/&#34;&gt;an &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; package named &lt;strong&gt;tinytex&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that installs a minimal LaTeX program and that automatically deals with differences between macOS and Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s how to install &lt;strong&gt;tinytex&lt;/strong&gt; so you can knit to pretty PDFs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the Packages in panel in RStudio to install &lt;strong&gt;tinytex&lt;/strong&gt; like you did above with &lt;strong&gt;tidyverse&lt;/strong&gt;. Alternatively, run &lt;code&gt;install.packages(&#34;tinytex&#34;)&lt;/code&gt; in the console.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;tinytex::install_tinytex()&lt;/code&gt; in the console.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait for a bit while &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; downloads and installs everything you need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The end! You should now be able to knit to PDF.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the course assignment template (for SSC442, see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/assignment/&#34;&gt;Assignments&lt;/a&gt; page), right-click to download it (don’t just click on it - that won’t work), open it in Rstudio, and without changing anything, click the “knit” button to test out your install. Your system should open a PDF that looks like something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;RenderedPDF.png&#34; width=&#34;962&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the Markdown and R Markdown sidebars for instructions on using the template.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes footnotes-end-of-document&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s a goofy name, but CRAN is where most &lt;code&gt;R&lt;/code&gt; packages—and R itself—lives.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pronounced “lay-tek” for those who are correct; or “lah-tex” to those who love goofy nerdy pronunciation. Technically speaking, the x is the “ch” sound in “Bach”, but most people just say it as “k”. While either saying “lay” or “lah” is correct, “layteks” is frowned upon because it clearly shows you’re not cool.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Rstudio (Posit) Cloud</title>
      <link>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/rstudiocloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/rstudiocloud/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#what-is-rstudio.cloud-posit.cloud&#34; id=&#34;toc-what-is-rstudio.cloud-posit.cloud&#34;&gt;What is &lt;del&gt;Rstudio.cloud&lt;/del&gt; Posit.cloud?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#setting-up-posit.cloud&#34; id=&#34;toc-setting-up-posit.cloud&#34;&gt;Setting up Posit.cloud&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;what-is-rstudio.cloud-posit.cloud&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What is &lt;del&gt;Rstudio.cloud&lt;/del&gt; Posit.cloud?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installing R and RStudio/Posit locally (on your computer) is the preferred method. Additionally, most MSU computer labs have R and RStudio installed. However, if your computer isn’t able to run RStudio, or you run into errors that we can’t troubleshoot, using RStudio Cloud is a viable alternative. Hosted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://posit.cloud&#34;&gt;Posit.cloud&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;del&gt;RStudio&lt;/del&gt; Posit Cloud is an online, web-based version of R and RStudio. On the “pro” side, it doesn’t require anything of your system except a functioning browser and can be up and running in a few minutes. The “con”, though, is that you must have an internet connection to use it, and it is limited to 25 hours per month for the free account (and $5/month for up to 75 hours per month). You shouldn’t need more than 25 hours per month, but if you’re very new to coding, it’s possible you will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Rstudio.cloud and Posit.cloud take you to the same site – posit.cloud. RStudio is in the process of rebranding to Posit. I have updated some, but not all, references here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;setting-up-posit.cloud&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Setting up Posit.cloud&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start by going to &lt;a href=&#34;https://posit.cloud&#34;&gt;Posit.cloud&lt;/a&gt; and create a free account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click “Your Workspace”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the top right corner, click on “New Project” and name it something like “SSC442”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;RSC1.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The “Files” tab in the lower-right pane shows your cloud project storage space. Let’s add a &lt;code&gt;templates&lt;/code&gt; folder and store the two course assignment templates there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/assignment/&#34;&gt;assignments&lt;/a&gt;, scroll down, and &lt;strong&gt;right-click on the Weekly Writing template and select “Save As…”&lt;/strong&gt; and save it to your desktop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do the same for the Lab Assignment template. Clicking on the link will open the text of the file in a browser window and you cannot just copy the text into an R file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With the files on your computer, go back to RStudio.cloud and in the Files tab, click on “New Folder” and name it &lt;code&gt;templates&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upload the templates one at a time to the folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the green up arrow to navigate the “Files” tab back to your main directory and create a folder for &lt;code&gt;Labs&lt;/code&gt; and one for &lt;code&gt;Weekly Writings&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the Lab Assignment template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the top of the template in the upper-left pane, you’ll see a warning that RStudio needs to install some packages. &lt;strong&gt;Click “Install”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;RSC3.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After R finishes installing packages (less than a minute), click the “Knit” button on the toolbar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RMarkdown will need to install a few more packages. Click “Yes”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;RSC4.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;10&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A pop-up window will open showing you the PDF of the rendered template. Congrats, you are ready to get to work!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;RSC5.png&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your RStudio.cloud version of RStudio will work just like a “local” install on a computer. Make sure you “Save As…” when you do your Lab or Weekly Writing assignments so that you don’t have to re-upload the templates. Keep a separate folder for each Lab inside the Labs to keep things clean in your workspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R Markdown</title>
      <link>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/rmarkdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/rmarkdown/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;div id=&#34;TOC&#34;&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#key-terms&#34; id=&#34;toc-key-terms&#34;&gt;Key terms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#add-chunks&#34; id=&#34;toc-add-chunks&#34;&gt;Add chunks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#chunk-names&#34; id=&#34;toc-chunk-names&#34;&gt;Chunk names&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#chunk-options&#34; id=&#34;toc-chunk-options&#34;&gt;Chunk options&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#chunk-fig.width-and-fig.height&#34; id=&#34;toc-chunk-fig.width-and-fig.height&#34;&gt;Chunk &lt;code&gt;fig.width&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;fig.height&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#inline-chunks&#34; id=&#34;toc-inline-chunks&#34;&gt;Inline chunks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#output-formats&#34; id=&#34;toc-output-formats&#34;&gt;Output formats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/reference/markdown/&#34;&gt;regular Markdown&lt;/a&gt; with R code and output sprinkled in. You can do everything you can with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/reference/markdown/&#34;&gt;regular Markdown&lt;/a&gt;, but you can incorporate graphs, tables, and other R output directly in your document. You can create HTML, PDF, and Word documents, PowerPoint and HTML presentations, websites, books, and even &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/flexdashboard/index.html&#34;&gt;interactive dashboards&lt;/a&gt; with R Markdown. This whole course website is created with R Markdown (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;a package named &lt;strong&gt;blogdown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;documentation for R Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is extremely comprehensive, and their &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/lesson-1.html&#34;&gt;tutorials&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/lesson-15.html&#34;&gt;cheatsheets&lt;/a&gt; are excellent—rely on those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have created a video walkthrough for using R Markdown for another course, but it is useful here. You can &lt;a href=&#34;https://mediaspace.msu.edu/media/R+Part+3/1_yigvqy1i&#34;&gt;see it here &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-film&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the most important things you’ll need to know about R Markdown in this class:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;key-terms&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key terms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Document&lt;/strong&gt;: A Markdown file where you type stuff&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chunk&lt;/strong&gt;: A piece of R code that is included in your document. It looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;markdown&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;```{r}
# Code goes here
```&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must be an empty line before and after the chunk. The final three backticks must be the only thing on the line—if you add more text, or if you forget to add the backticks, or accidentally delete the backticks, your document will not knit correctly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knit&lt;/strong&gt;: When you “knit” a document, R runs each of the chunks sequentially and converts the output of each chunk into Markdown. R then runs the knitted document through &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org/&#34;&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt; to convert it to HTML or PDF or Word (or whatever output you’ve selected). We will always use PDF for this course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can knit by clicking on the “Knit” button at the top of the editor window, or by pressing &lt;code&gt;⌘⇧K&lt;/code&gt; on macOS or &lt;code&gt;control + shift + K&lt;/code&gt; on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/assignments/knit-button.png&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;add-chunks&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Add chunks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are three ways to insert chunks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;⌘⌥I&lt;/code&gt; on macOS or &lt;code&gt;control + alt + I&lt;/code&gt; on Windows&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click on the “Insert” button at the top of the editor window&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/reference/insert-chunk.png&#34; width=&#34;30%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manually type all the backticks and curly braces (don’t do this)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;chunk-names&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chunk names&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add names to chunks to make it easier to navigate your document. If you click on the little dropdown menu at the bottom of your editor in RStudio, you can see a table of contents that shows all the headings and chunks. If you name chunks, they’ll appear in the list. If you don’t include a name, the chunk will still show up, but you won’t know what it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/reference/chunk-toc.png&#34; width=&#34;40%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To add a name, include it immediately after the &lt;code&gt;{r&lt;/code&gt; in the first line of the chunk. Names cannot contain spaces, but they can contain underscores and dashes. &lt;strong&gt;All chunk names in your document must be unique.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;markdown&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;```{r name-of-this-chunk}
# Code goes here
```&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;chunk-options&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Chunk options&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a bunch of different options you can set for each chunk. You can see a complete list in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/rmarkdown-reference.pdf&#34;&gt;RMarkdown Reference Guide&lt;/a&gt; or at &lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.org/knitr/options/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;knitr&lt;/strong&gt;’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Options go inside the &lt;code&gt;{r}&lt;/code&gt; section of the chunk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;markdown&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;```{r name-of-this-chunk, warning=FALSE, message=FALSE}
# Code goes here
```&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common chunk options are these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;fig.width=5&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;fig.height=3&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;em&gt;or whatever number you want&lt;/em&gt;): Set the dimensions for figures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;echo=FALSE&lt;/code&gt;: The code is not shown in the final document, but the results are&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;message=FALSE&lt;/code&gt;: Any messages that R generates (like all the notes that appear after you load a package) are omitted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;warning=FALSE&lt;/code&gt;: Any warnings that R generates are omitted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;include=FALSE&lt;/code&gt;: The chunk still runs, but the code and results are not included in the final document. Don’t use this on your labs as we need to see your work, but do use this for your final project when the output is to be polished and clean.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also set chunk options by clicking on the little gear icon in the top right corner of any chunk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/reference/chunk-options.png&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;chunk-fig.width-and-fig.height&#34; class=&#34;section level3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chunk &lt;code&gt;fig.width&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;fig.height&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a code chunk includes a plot (like from &lt;code&gt;ggplot&lt;/code&gt;), the “canvas” size used can affect the output. You may have noticed if you plot directly in Rstudio, the plot resizes when you change the pane size. Each chunk has its own canvas size, and you can change that. So, if you have a chunk with a large plot, you can change the &lt;code&gt;fig.width=7.5&lt;/code&gt; in the chunk options. Note that units default to inches, so no more than 7.5 will fit on a regular-sized sheet of paper (or appropriately sized PDF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;inline-chunks&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inline chunks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also include R output directly in your text, which is really helpful if you want to report numbers from your analysis. To do this, use &lt;code&gt;`r r_code_here`&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s generally easiest to calculate numbers in a regular chunk beforehand and then use an inline chunk to display the value in your text. For instance, this document…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;markdown&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;```{r find-avg-mpg, echo=FALSE}
avg_mpg &amp;lt;- mean(mtcars$mpg)
```

The average fuel efficiency for cars from 1974 was `r round(avg_mpg, 1)` miles per gallon.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;… would knit into this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average fuel efficiency for cars from 1974 was 20.1 miles per gallon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;output-formats&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Output formats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can specify what kind of document you create when you knit in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/reference/markdown/#front-matter&#34;&gt;YAML front matter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;yaml&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;title: &amp;quot;My document&amp;quot;
output:
  html_document: default
  pdf_document: default
  word_document: default&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also click on the down arrow on the “Knit” button to choose the output &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; generate the appropriate YAML. If you click on the gear icon next to the “Knit” button and choose “Output options”, you change settings for each specific output type, like default figure dimensions or whether or not a table of contents is included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../../../../../../img/reference/output-options.png&#34; width=&#34;35%&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first output type listed under &lt;code&gt;output:&lt;/code&gt; will be what is generated when you click on the “Knit” button or press the keyboard shortcut (&lt;code&gt;⌘⇧K&lt;/code&gt; on macOS; &lt;code&gt;control + shift + K&lt;/code&gt; on Windows). If you choose a different output with the “Knit” button menu, that output will be moved to the top of the &lt;code&gt;output&lt;/code&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The indentation of the YAML section matters, especially when you have settings nested under each output type. Here’s what a typical &lt;code&gt;output&lt;/code&gt; section might look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;yaml&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
title: &amp;quot;My document&amp;quot;
author: &amp;quot;My name&amp;quot;
date: &amp;quot;January 13, 2020&amp;quot;
output: 
  html_document: 
    toc: yes
    fig_caption: yes
    fig_height: 8
    fig_width: 10
  pdf_document: 
    latex_engine: xelatex  # More modern PDF typesetting engine
    toc: yes
  word_document: 
    toc: yes
    fig_caption: yes
    fig_height: 4
    fig_width: 5
---&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data</title>
      <link>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ssc442kirkpatrick.netlify.app/resource/data/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of places to find data related to public policy and administration (as well as data on pretty much any topic you want) online:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyletter.com/data-is-plural&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data is Plural newsletter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Jeremy Singer-Vine sends a weekly newsletter of the most interesting public datasets he’s found. You should subscribe to it. &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1wZhPLMCHKJvwOkP4juclhjFgqIY8fQFMemwKL2c64vk/edit#gid=0&#34;&gt;He also has an archive of all the datasets he’s highlighted.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://toolbox.google.com/datasetsearch&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Google Dataset Search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Google indexes thousands of public datasets; search for them here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/datasets&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kaggle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Kaggle hosts machine learning competitions where people compete to create the fastest, most efficient, most predictive algorithms. A byproduct of these competitions is a host of fascinating datasets that are generally free and open to the public. See, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/hugomathien/soccer&#34;&gt;the European Soccer Database&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/rtatman/salem-witchcraft-dataset&#34;&gt;Salem Witchcraft Dataset&lt;/a&gt; or results from an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kaggle.com/rtatman/oreo-flavors-tastetest-ratings&#34;&gt;Oreo flavors taste test&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Note: when you are asked in an assignment or project to find data, Kaggle is not a valid source. You learn nothing about farming by getting fruit from the market. Similarly, you learn nothing about data analysis by getting pre-packaged data from Kaggle.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.threesixtygiving.org/data/data-registry/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;360Giving&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Dozens of British foundations follow a standard file format for sharing grant data and have made that data available online.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://us-cities.survey.okfn.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;US City Open Data Census&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: More than 100 US cities have committed to sharing dozens of types of data, including data about crime, budgets, campaign finance, lobbying, transit, and zoning. This site from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://sunlightfoundation.com/&#34;&gt;Sunlight Foundation&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.codeforamerica.org//&#34;&gt;Code for America&lt;/a&gt; collects this data and rates cities by how well they’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political science and economics datasets&lt;/strong&gt;: There’s a wealth of data available for political science- and economics-related topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/briatte/srqm/wiki/Data&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;François Briatte’s extensive curated lists&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Includes data from/about intergovernmental organizations (IGOs), nongovernmental organizations (NGOs), public opinion surveys, parliaments and legislatures, wars, human rights, elections, and municipalities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/leeper/poliscitoys/issues/1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeper’s list of political science datasets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Good short list of useful datasets, divided by type of data (country-level data, survey data, social media data, event data, text data, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/erikgahner/PolData&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erik Gahner’s list of political science datasets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: Huge list of useful datasets, divided by topic (governance, elections, policy, political elites, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geospatial datasets&lt;/strong&gt;: For our geospatial unit, many entities (government agencies, etc.) post repositories of spatial data via arcgis.com, which is owned by ESRI, the company that makes the predominant commercial GIS software. The data owner decides what data to post and how to present it, but arcgis.com provides the hosting. R has excellent geospatial functionalities, so we cover (when time permits) geospatial data. It is easy to find geospatial data to import into R. Here are a few:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gis-michigan.opendata.arcgis.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State of Michigan Open Data Portal&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hifld-geoplatform.opendata.arcgis.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Homeland Infrastructure Foundation-Level Data (HIFLD)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://coel.maps.arcgis.com/apps/webappviewer/index.html?id=076f31109b974149ac3e1c2379aac8d6&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City of East Lansing Data Viewer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
